Guide to the Frank Baker Collection of Wesleyana and British Methodism, 1536-1996 and undated RL.00413
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Frank Baker collection of Wesleyana and British Methodism
1536-1996 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Baker, Frank, 1910-1999
RL.00413
50 Linear Feet approximately 18,000 items
Frank Baker (1910-1999) was a faculty member at Duke University in history, an expert on Wesleyan Methodism, and a rare book and manuscripts collector. The Frank Baker Collection of Wesleyana and British Methodism, 1536-1996 and undated, comprises correspondence, writings, local histories, printed items, engravings, and many other manuscript materials that date from the earliest years of Methodism to its worldwide expansion up to the 20th century. The collection includes the correspondence of two of the most important founders of Methodism, John and Charles Wesley, as well as correspondence from members of the Wesley family. Collection also includes correspondence from many of the key figures in 18th and 19th century history of British Methodism: Joseph Benson, Jabez Bunting, Adam Clarke, Thomas Coke, James Everett, John Fletcher, Mary (Bosanquet) Fletcher, Selina Hastings, Countess of Huntingdon, Elizabeth (Ritchie) Mortimer, George Osborn, Hester Ann Rogers, Richard Tabraham, and Thomas Wride. Other materials include church records and registers, account books, autograph albums, broadsides (notices), circular letters, engravings, maps, sermons, scrapbooks, photographs, and memorabilia. Topics covered by the materials include the life and training of Methodist clergy; the religious life of women; biography and portraiture of Methodists; spirituality; Protestantism in art; and the debate between Arminianism and Calvinism in the early church. Organizational history in the collection covers several branches of the 18th and 19th century church, including Wesleyan Methodism, Primitive Methodism, missions, and missionary societies.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In addition, some originals in the collection are restricted except for use under direct staff supervision. Patrons must use photocopies of originals.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The materials in the Frank Baker Collection of Wesleyana and British Methodism were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as purchases and gifts from 1961-2007.
Collection Overview
The Frank Baker Collection of Wesleyana and British Methodism, 1536-1996 and undated, comprises a vast range of original correspondence, writings, local histories, printed items, engravings, and many other manuscript materials that date from the earliest years of Methodism to its expansion throughout the British Empire during the 18th, 19th, and early 20th centuries. The collection includes the correspondence of two of the most important founders of Methodism, John and Charles Wesley, as well as correspondence from members of the Wesley family, including Samuel Wesley, Sr. (1662-1735), Sarah (Gwynne) Wesley (1726-1822) and the Gwynne family, and the children of Charles and Sarah Wesley: Charles Wesley, Junior (1757-1834), Sarah (Sally) Wesley (1759-1828), and Samuel Wesley (1766-1837).
Additionally, correspondence from many of the key figures in 18th and 19th century history of British Methodism greatly extends the collection's breadth of coverage. Among others, these groups of correspondence include Joseph Benson, Jabez Bunting, Adam Clarke, Thomas Coke, James Everett, John Fletcher, Mary (Bosanquet) Fletcher, Selina Hastings, Countess of Huntingdon, Elizabeth (Ritchie) Mortimer, George Osborn, Hester Ann Rogers, Richard Tabraham, and Thomas Wride.
The collection materials cover many topics, including: the life and training of clergy women correspondence and diaries; the religious life of women; biography; portraiture; spiritual topics; Protestantism as depicted in art; and the debate between Arminianism and Calvinism in the early church. Organizational history in the collection covers several branches of the 18th and 19th century church, including Wesleyan Methodism, Primitive Methodism, missions, and missionary societies.
Formats of materials include church records and registers, account books, autograph albums, broadsides (notices), circular letters, engravings, maps, sermons, scrapbooks, class tickets, photographs, photocopies of original manuscripts, memorabilia, and realia.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is divided into ten series: Wesley Family, Correspondence, Methodist Class and Band Tickets, Printed Materials, Subject Files, Visual Materials, Writings and Addresses, Volumes, and the F. F. Bretherton Papers. Finally, the Small Collections Series describes twelve small related Methodist history manuscript collections cataloged and housed as separate collections.
Related Material
Provenance of materials: The provenance of materials in the Frank Baker Collection of Wesleyana and British Methodism is both complex and incomplete. Baker built his collection over the course of several decades, from a wide variety of sources: booksellers, auction houses, historical societies, colleagues, and many people who wrote to him about items in their family or personal collections. Where possible, such provenance documentation is housed in folders or boxes adjacent to holograph items. More often, though, authenticating the full history of an item would require broader research in both this collection and the closely-related Frank Baker Papers.
Three series in the latter can prove useful for establishing what may be thought of as the later history of items (that is, how FB came to acquire them and pass them to Duke): the Subject Files, searched by name, place, or topic; Correspondence, particularly prior to FB's move from England to the U.S. in 1960; and the Baker Collections Files, which contain much correspondence detailing the gradual transfer of FB's collections to the Duke University Libraries from 1961 through the early 2000s.
The early history of items (how they passed from their creators down through the 19th and early 20th centuries to FB's immediate source), is more difficult to trace, though possible in many instances. Many otherwise obscure or anonymous handwritten notes on holographs and early transcriptions in the collection can be traced to one or more of a number of historians, writers, and collectors whose lives date from the late 18th century all the way to the mid-1950s. More information about all of these men is available elsewhere in this finding aid, but their names and dates are given here in chronological order: James Everett (1784-1872); Thomas Marriott (1786-1852); George Osborn (1808-1891); Lucas Tyernan (1820-1889); George Stampe (1836-1918); Marmaduke Riggall (1851-1927); and F. F. Bretherton (1868-1956). Bretherton, whom FB knew well from his work in the Wesley Historical Society, is often the most immediate connection between FB and the earlier historians and collectors.
Related collections: The Frank Baker Collection of Wesleyana and British Methodism forms part of a larger group of collections gathered by FB during his long career as a collector and scholar. These collections, plus others housed in both the Rubenstein Library and the Duke Divinity School Library, contain extensive related materials on many of the topics documented in this collection. Rubenstein Library collections are listed first, followed by Divinity School collections.
Frank Baker Collection of Wesleyana and British Methodism (printed materials division). Holds hundreds of editions of John Wesley's sermons, hymns, journals, and editorial works, plus such organizational materials as minutes of the Methodist Conferences. These materials can be searched in the online catalog by individual title, by genre, or by using the full name of the collection in the author field: Frank Baker Collection of Wesleyana and British Methodism.
Frank Baker papers, 1641-2002 and undated [catalog record]. Contains FB's individual scholarship, as distinct from his work in the WWEP. Although in theory an entirely separate collection from the WWA, in practice there are numerous overlaps between the collections. The Libraries and Archives Series documents much of FB's correspondence with and visits to libraries around the world, mainly in the 1960s and 1970s, in the effort to document and gather as many Wesley archival and printed materials as possible. The Correspondence Series contains FB's letters to and from many of same correspondents and colleagues who appear in the Wesley Works Archive. And the enormous Subject Files are rich in materials related to the project, especially the numerous indexes of Wesley's letters and other writings to be found in the Card Files Subseries.
Wesley Works archive, 1676-1996 and undated, bulk 1724-1791, 1960-1996 [catalog record]. Working papers of the Wesley Works Editorial Project (WWEP), as gathered by FB during his years as the WWEP's General Editor, Textual Editor, and main bibliographer.
Frank Baker collection of Methodist circuit plans, 1777-1984 [catalog record].
Wesley holograph letters also appear in two small sub-collections of the Wesleyana manuscripts, the Sarah Crosby papers, 1760-1804 and the Perronet Family papers, 1752-1855
JW autograph letters are also contained in two small non-Baker collections in the Rubenstein Library, the Wesley family papers, 1726-1889 [catalog record and the G. (George) Story papers, 1738-1818
The Frank Baker Microfilm Collection (Divinity Library) houses hundreds of microfilms from archives all over the world, collected at FB's request from the 1960s-1980s, containing thousands of images of Wesley manuscripts and printed materials used by the WWEP to gather as many as possible of the approximately 4000 editions of Wesley's publications to appear during his lifetime. Inquire at the Divinity Library Reference Desk.
The Frank Baker Photocopies Collection (Divinity Library) contains photocopies of several hundred of the rare monographs housed in the Rubenstein Library. These were often FB's working copies of books he had already sold or given to the library, and are similar though not identical to the many photocopies in the WWA.
Duke Divinity School: Center for Studies in the Wesleyan Tradition. Contains numerous original and digitized texts on Wesleyan and Methodist studies, as well as links to many other archival sources on the Web. A sub-page of this site serves as the online home of the Wesley Works Editorial Project.
In addition to this general list, other related materials in the Duke Libraries are cited in certain series notes. Inquire at the Divinity Library Reference Desk.
Methodist Church -- England -- History; Arminianism -- Great Britain -- History -- 18th century; Women -- Religious life; Methodism -- History; Class meetings, Methodist; Clergy -- Correspondence; Calvinistic Methodists -- Great Britain -- History -- 18th century; Church records and registers -- England; Protestantism in art; Women -- Diaries; Methodists -- Biography; Portraits, British; Women -- England -- Correspondence; Realia; Scrapbooks; Black-and-white photographs; Memorabilia; Diaries; Maps; Account books; Autograph albums; Broadsides (notices); Circular letters; Sermons; Engravings (prints); Wesley, Charles, 1757-1834; Wesley, John, 1703-1791; Wesley family; Wesley, Charles, 1707-1788; Rogers, Hester Ann, 1756-1794; Tabraham, Richard, 1792-1878; Osborn, G. (George), 1808-1891; Primitive Methodist Church (Great Britain); Mortimer, Elizabeth, 1754-1835; Newton, Robert, 1780-1854; Methodist Church (Great Britain) -- Missions; Methodist Church -- England -- Clergy; Fletcher, Mary, 1739-1815; Huntingdon, Selina Hastings, Countess of, 1707-1791; Everett, James, 1784-1872; Fletcher, John, 1729-1785; England -- Pictorial works; England -- Maps -- Early works to 1800; Coke, Thomas, 1747-1814; Clarke, Adam, ca. 1762-1832; Bunting, Jabez, 1779-1858; Benson, Joseph, 1749-1821; Baker, Frank, 1910-1999; Wesley, Sarah, 1726-1822; Wesley, Samuel, 1662-1735; Wesleyan Methodist Church -- History; Wesley, Sarah, 1759-1828; Wesleyan Methodist Church -- West Indies, British; Wesleyan Methodist Church -- Missions -- Africa; Wride, Thomas, 1733-1807; Wesleyan Methodist Missionary Society
- Wesley Family Series, 1700-1996 and undated, 18 boxes, approx. 1800 items
  Scope and Contents note
  Documents three generations of the family, but especially the lives of John and Charles Wesley. The series is divided into subseries by family member. The three largest manuscripts subseries are those for John Wesley (1703-1791), Charles Wesley (1707-1788), and Sarah Wesley (1759-1826), the daughter of Charles. The John Wesley Papers are mainly original autograph letters (outgoing and incoming) spanning some fifty-five years of his life. There is also one forgery, several 18th or 19th century handwritten copies, and one engraved facsimile. John's letters contain no one frequent correspondent; the Charles Wesley Papers are dominated by Charles' letters to Samuel Lloyd, a friend and sometime legal and financial advisor in London. These draw a portrait of almost twenty years of their friendship. There are also letters to his wife and children, and to important church figures such as John Fletcher and Joseph Benson.
  The Sarah Wesley Letters and Poems, though little known, constitute one of the highlights of the Wesley Family Papers--Frank Baker thought it the largest collection in the world of her manuscript poems. There are also over forty complete letters and fragments, spanning forty years of her life and including the only marriage proposal she is known to have received.
  The manuscript portion of the series is rounded out by several small groups of letters from other family members related directly to Charles: his wife, Sarah, and her sisters, his two sons, Charles and Samuel; and two grandsons. The series ends with the large Wesley Family Portraits Subseries, some 1000 engraved prints of family members, scenes from their lives, and places associated with them. Almost half of these images are of John Wesley, one of the most frequently-painted portrait subjects of 18th century England.
  Letters and writings of the Wesley family are arranged in subseries by family member, in chronological order by date of birth: Samuel Wesley, Sr. (1662-1735); John Wesley (1703-1791); Charles Wesley (1707-1788); Sarah [Gwynne] Wesley (1726-1822); Charles Wesley, Junior (1757-1834); Sarah (Sally) Wesley (1759-1828); and Samuel Wesley (1766-1837).
  - Information folder (Box WF1)
  - Specimen of Mr. Wesley's Short-hand Diary; Specimens of some of the earliest Society Tickets, 19th c.? (Box WF1)
    John Wesley and others developed a system of shorthand for communications and writings, some examples of which can be found in this collection. This single undated printed sheet contains a sample of about 20 lines in Wesley's own shorthand - without a key, however - originating from a journal entry from 1740. The facing page contains illustrations of ten Methodist Society Tickets from the 18th century.
  - Samuel Wesley, Sr. (1662-1735) Subseries, 1700, 1 item
    Church of England clergyman, poet, and father of John Wesley (1703-1791) and Charles Wesley (1707-1788).
    - Wesley, Samuel, Epworth, to Mr. Justice Hook, London, 1700 July 10 (Box WF1)
  - John Wesley (1703-1791) Subseries, 1710, 1734-1826, 1860-1903, 1977, and undated, 44 items
    Letters written by John Wesley to family, fellow preachers and members of his congregation. The majority of these letters are abrupt, aimed at answering specific questions or resolving particular concerns, but others are more expansive. The 1735/6 letter, composed as Wesley was on his way to Georgia, relates events of the voyage and singles out General Oglethorpe for praise. Writing to Lord Rowdon on May 18, 1760, Wesley opposes "the simplicity of the Gospel" with "Philosophical Religion."
    Several letters are either addressed or refer to individuals whose manuscripts appear elsewhere in the Baker Wesleyana Collection, especially John Fletcher, Elizabeth (Ritchie) Mortimer, and Sarah Crosby. The letter to Miss Sparrow of Jan. 14, 1779, first passes on an anecdote that Fletcher told about Voltaire, then goes on to present Wesley's scathing views on the French writer and his successes. On June 3, 1774, writing to Sarah Crosby, Wesley worries that Elizabeth Ritchie might succumb to temptation and instructs Mrs. Crosby to watch over her. And in another letter to her several years later (May 11, 1780), he turns his concern to Crosby herself, assuring her that he will keep her writing a secret, burning the originals and transcribing only what he wishes to keep for himself; further, he questions her about her predilection to vices, urging her to speak openly about herself to him, but noting that he does not make a habit of speaking about himself to others so as not to hurt them.
    Arranged in chronological order.
    Conditions Governing Access note
    [NOTE: Originals housed in Box WF 1 available by prior request only. Use copies for most but not all of the originals are in Box WF 4. Please consult with a reference archivist if there is no use copy.
    - Prid[eau]x, Selby, London, to the Rev'd Mr. [John] Westly, Oxon, 1734 Apr. 9 (Box WF1)
      Endorsed by John Wesley: "Selby. April 9, 1734. + / New birth." FB's extensive note about this letter and its writer, ca. 1976, quoted in full: "PM, 9/AP. 4 pp. 4t0, part of red seal. Spelt 'Westly'.; Gives copy of S's letter to Bp. Of [?] from memory, 'Yewterday I heard ye Rev. Mr. A. Swear, Mr. B. S, talk B. & gets D-k frequently. Mr. C. is a d-n f Priest. Mr. D and Mr. E are called D-n Priests. Mr. E pays nobody his D-ts.' He writes from pity, not malice. Selby not in Dick's [Heitzenrater] diss., but Green, p. 191: 'Prideax Selby, the son of a merchant from Holy Island in Northumberland, had become a member of Lincoln as a servitor on 25th November, 1731, and was elected to a scholarship on 22nd February, 1733; Wesley talked to him about Communion and by October he was one of the little company who made their Communion at Christ Church on Sunday mornings.'"
    - Wesley, John, on board the Simmonds, to [Sir John Phillips], 1735/6 Jan. 20 (Box WF1)
      FB's typewritten note accompanies this letter: "A contemporary copy of an important letter written by JW as he set sail for America. The letter is genuine, but the handwriting is not Wesley's. Cf. the photostat of the original in Wesley's hand, written to Sir John Phillips, and endorsed by him. Wesley wrote another copy to Dr. John Burton, one of the Trustees for the Colony of Georgia."
    - Wesley, John, Bristol, to Charles Wesley, Moorfields, 1741 Feb. 10 (Box WF1)
      Penciled note: "Forgery. FB."
    - Wesley, John, Bristol, to Mrs. Jones, n.p., 1746 Aug. 4 (transcription) (Box WF1)
      Original handwritten transcription, presumably contemporary, was made by Thomas Richards, who then appended a note of his own. This pair of letters in their entirety was then transcribed by R. O. Jones, circa 1860s. Richards was one of Wesley's earliest itinerant preachers; for more information, see entry on Richards in the Frank Baker Papers, Subject Files, from which this item was transferred.
    - Wesley, John, Journal pages and notes, 1751 Dec. 14-23, AN, two pages (Box WF1)
    - Wesley, John, Sligo, to [Lord Rowdon], n.p., 1760 May 18 (Box WF1)
    - Band ticket endorsed "D. Carnaby" [in John Wesley's hand], 1762 Feb. (Box WF1)
    - Wesley, John, to Mr. Hopper; Cork, 1762 June 18 (Box WF1)
    - Wesley, John, London, to Matthew Lowes, n.p., 1762 June 25 (Box WF1)
      Facsimile "engraved by W. Collard from a series of autograph letters from the Rev'd J. Wesley to Mr. Matthew Lowes, now in the Possession of Mr. T. Sopwith, Newcastle on Tyne," undated.
    - Wesley, John, London, to Thomas Rankin, Plymouth Dock, 1765 Jan. 26 (Box WF1)
    - Wesley, John, Bristol, to [?], Coolylough, 1769 July 4 (Box WF1)
      Also includes transcription of a letter from Adam Clarke, City Road, to John Cayley, 1808 Feb. 25; transcription by W.H. Allmutt, Bodleian Library, Oxford, 1871 Dec. 8. Transferred from the Frank Baker Papers, Subject Files, Oxford.
    - Wesley, John, notes on reading a document on "The Baptism of the Spirit", circa 1772 (Box WF1)
      Original missing. Copy available in folder.
      Photocopy accompanied by researcher note: Single sheet (two page) document in Wesley's hand, numbered p.3 and p.4, recording Wesley's comments on a long document of at least 38 pages written by either John Fletcher or Joseph Benson, which is not known to survive.
    - Wesley, John, London, to Sammy [Samuel Bardsley], Hatten, Loughborough, 1773 Jan. 29 (Box WF1)
      Handwritten transcription by Charles A. Federer, 1903 June 4. A penciled note, undated, points out that JW's closing phrase, "Ivy Leaves grow on Walls," does not appear in the printed version of this letter.
    - Wesley, John, to Mr. Hopper, at the Orphan House, Newcastle upon Tyne; London, 1773 Aug. 7 (Box WF1)
    - Wesley, J[ohn], Bristol, to James Barry, n.p., 1773 Oct. 1 (Box WF1)
      Handwritten transcription by Wm. Lindley, Swansea, 1861 May 10, who describes Barry as "an early Methodist Preacher."
    - Wesley, John, Edinburgh, to Mrs. [Sarah] Crosby, 1774 June 3 (Box WF1)
      Provenance: housed with the use copy in Box WF 4 is a photocopied invoice from Charles Hamilton to FB regarding the letter, undated.
    - Wesley, John, to Mr. Jno. Crook, 1775 Dec. 15 (Box WF1)
    - Wesley, John, "I give six pounds to be divided among the six poor Men, named by the Assistants, who shall carry by body to the grave...," will, circa 1776 (Box WF1)
      Manuscript fragment containing will, one page, signed as by John Wesley. A penciled note on verso, probably in FB's hand, dates item to circa 1776.
    - Foley, Ambrose, Quintain Green near Hales-Owen, Shropshire, to the Reverend Mr. [John] Westley, n.p., 1778 Mar. 18 (Box WF1)
    - Wesley, John, n.p., to ?, n.p., 1778 Nov. 3 (Box WF1)
      Signed fragment containing part of final sentence, closing, and JW's signature. Mounted in two page scrapbook labeled "John Wesley 1703-1791," which also includes an engraving of JW, a piece of ivy from his grave, and a silhouette of "Mrs. Vizelle. Wesley's Wife."
      Provenance: discovered loose in FB's papers, apparently having come to him from F. F. Bretherton. A penciled note signed by FFB states: "not in Standard. Do not think this is Wesley's h/w."
    - Wesley, John, to "Miss Sparrow, No. 2," 1779 Jan. 14 (Box WF1)
    - Wesley, John, Newcastle, to Sarah Crosby, [1780] May 11 (Box WF1)
    - Wesley, John, Darlington, to Zachariah Udal, 1784 June 13 (Box WF1)
    - Tennant, Thomas, [on behalf of John Wesley], London, to [Samuel] Bardsley, 1785 Feb. 12 (Box WF1)
    - "Mr. Wesleys acct. for the Year 1786," 1786 (Box WF1)
      Unsigned original receipt, transferred from the Frank Baker Papers, Subject Files. Item was filed there under the name of John Atlay, although FB's own typewritten transcription indicates it is likely in the hand of Wesley's Book Steward at the time, George Whitfield.
    - Wesley, John, London, to Rev'd Mr. Bull, 1787 Jan. 17 (Box WF1)
      Scope and Contents
      Missing. Photocopy provided.
    - Wesley, John, Cork, to Hannah Ball, 1787 May 9 (Box WF1)